<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Muld sacke: or The apologie of Hic Mulier: to the late declamation against her Exprest in a short exclamation. Non est mollis è terris ad astra via. Muld sacke, muld sacke.</title>
            <author>Hic Mulier.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16827</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11273)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16827)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Muld sacke: or The apologie of Hic Mulier: to the late declamation against her Exprest in a short exclamation. Non est mollis è terris ad astra via. Muld sacke, muld sacke.</title>
                  <author>Hic Mulier.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Richard Meighen, and are to be sold at his shops vnder Saint Clements Church, and at Westminster Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Hic mulier.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut of John Cottington, copied from the engraving of Renold Elstracke.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-D4).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf contains verses.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hic mulier --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:1"/>
            <head>MVLD SACKE, His gratulatorie thankefulneſſe to <hi>Hic Mulier,</hi> for her dedication.</head>
            <l>IN recompence, ſweet Heart, of thy ſweet Booke,</l>
            <l>My Picture I thee ſend, whereon 'pray looke.</l>
            <l>All Maydes, and Bookes, not thus rewarded bee,</l>
            <l>Loue hath a Tongue, although no Eyes to ſee.</l>
            <l>Then fayreſt faire, in this ſweet little frame,</l>
            <l>My Heart and Selfe I proſtrate to thy Name,</l>
            <l>Vowing my Sword, my yellow Band, and Feather,</l>
            <l>My ſmoking Pipe, Scarfe, Garters, Roſes, either</l>
            <l>With my ſpruſe Bootes, neat Hornes, and all I giue</l>
            <l>To thee, by whoſe ſweet loue, I breathe, reigne. liue.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:1"/>
            <p>Muld Sacke: OR The Apologie of <hi>Hic Mulier: To the late Declamation againſt her.</hi> Expreſt in a ſhort Exclamation. <hi>Non eſt mollis è terris ad astra via.</hi> Muld Sacke, Muld Sacke.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>standing man</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Richard Mewhen,</hi> and are to be ſold at his <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnder Saint <hi>Clements</hi> Church, and at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:2"/>
            <head>TO MY PROFESSED FRIEND, MVLD SACKE, None of the leaſt of the ancient Societie of Chimney-Sweepers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had wearied my vnſetled brayne, with the finding out of a fit Patron, or indifferent Iudge, for the defence or equall cenſure of my Apologeticall anſwer, to a bitter Declamation, lately come abroad againſt me, I could hit of none more fit then your <hi>Gaffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> whoſe equall carriage, both to mee, and <hi>Haec Vir</hi> (ſince I did firſt know you) hath beene ſuch, that it can be hardly iudged, to whom you are moſt inclined. One day you weare yellow Bands, Feathers, Scarffes; cuts your haire and powders it, paints your face ſo all the weeke, that vpon Sunday, a pound of ſope will not reduce it
<pb facs="tcp:16827:3"/> to the right colour; you dance, ſing, and vſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther jouiall conceits, wherein I (poore Wench) much delight; but when I looke vpon your Hornes, your Garters, Roſes, and other your Feminine maſculine faſhions, then J perceiue you participate alſo with <hi>Haec Vir,</hi> and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently affected to vs both. Wherefore (good <hi>Gaffer</hi>) ſeeing Truth hath yeelded it ſelfe to be the Clyent of my anſwer, let this poore Apologie find ſuch rich fauour with you, that you will become Patron thereof, cenſuring this Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine, rather by my paſsions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, at the writing thereof, then by the iudicious or formall dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of it,</p>
            <p>In the doing whereof, you ſhall oblige me to continue</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, ſo long as you correſpond HIC MVLIER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:3"/>
            <head>MVLD SACKE: OR THE APOLOGIE OF <hi>HIC MVLIER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Title (being <hi>Hic Mulier</hi>) of your Declamation, giues me iuſt cauſe, to ranke you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe Thraſonical Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, who dare enter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with none, but with the weake, vnarmed, or dead. You haue taken armes, not only againſt a Woman,<note place="margin">Timiditas eſt, &amp; quod maius eſt amittere, &amp; quod minus eſt capere, <hi>Eurip. in Phoen.</hi>
               </note> but againſt the weakeſt of Women, yea ſo weake, that the breath of a Souldier is able to throw her vpon her backe; you haue wounded a Man, but more to your ſhame, a dead Man. Before I come to my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, let me expoſtulate a little with you; Who bee theſe good Women, whom you ſo complementally magnifie in your Declamation? or, where doe they dwell? It appeareth to me you haue beene a trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler (therefore are Licentiate) and perhaps in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of Arabia, haue ſeene ſome one, whom you
<pb facs="tcp:16827:4"/> grace with ſuch excellencies; but that ſuch a Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix ſhould multiplie to a world-full of good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, no man (except mad) will beleeue you.</p>
            <p>I doe confeſſe they are the Seminaries of propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, the ſupporters of mankind, (as you rightly terme them) and ſo are we.<note place="margin">Perpetuum, &amp; neceſſarium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſt mulier, <hi>Stob.</hi>
               </note> The greateſt praiſe that (by the moſt wiſe) hath beene giuen vs therereby, is, that we are, <hi>mala neceſſaria,</hi> and that's all: your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hyperbolicall praiſes are paradoxes not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. I doe confeſſe there be ſome (whom you call good) faire, and chaſte, but thoſe are commonly proude; ſome deformed and vertuous, thoſe bee ſcoulds; ſome ſociable, thoſe are yeelding, not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable caſtles;<note place="margin">Ego mulieri hoc vnum credo, quod à morte non reuiuiſcat, <hi>Anlep.</hi>
               </note> ſayleable, not vnſayleable Riuers; moueable not vnmoueable Seas; Helpers, but not truſtie; Centinels, but ſleepie; ſignes, but deceitfull; true guides, but full of danger; Balmes that ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome cure; honoures, but euery day periſhing, and ſuch graces as <hi>Seneca</hi> neuer praiſed, but in his mad or doting age; or (as you ſay) with <hi>Sophocles</hi> preſented them as they ſhould be: but I with <hi>Euripides</hi> praiſe them as they are, and ſhall admire with you and ſay, O you rare good women,<note place="margin">Rarum eſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieris benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, apud <hi>Stob.</hi>
               </note> you are modeſt when milde, young when vertuous, glorious when chaſte; looke not to find your name in this exclamation, but I ſhall write it with a pen of I know not what, and vpon paper I know not where; I write now with a Gooſe quill, on white paper, the deedes of a dull leaden age, blackiſh, I ſhould ſay, brokiſh age.</p>
            <p>To come then to my anſwere, wherein I will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſſe your farre borrowed epithites, and helliſh compariſons applyed vnto vs, and only will anſwere
<pb facs="tcp:16827:4"/> the more materiall points of your accuſation;<note place="margin">A ſimilibus, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milia non lu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s fi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Ariſt. Rhet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and thereafter diſcouer the abuſes of <hi>Haec Vir</hi> whom you dare not point at, much leſſe challenge.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I anſwere that thoſe imputations you doe lay againſt me, are the chiefe <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> the moſt honourable ends, the only vertues, I ayme at, And therefore no maruell although enuied, it hath beene ſo <hi>à principio;</hi> for what greater glorie can come to the maſculine woman (as you terme her) then to ouerrule her parents and husband?<note place="margin">Mulieri impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare in parentes, out maritam no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concedit natura, <hi>Pub. Mim.</hi>
               </note> to be ſo pitifull that ſhe cuts the hayre of her head, to couer their ſhallow braines, or hornes; ſo ſtout that ſhee diſarmes the Martiall, degrades Knights by vnſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (or rather oft ſpurring) them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antonius Silui<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a Venetian, hauing a faire wife, deuiſed a rare locke <hi>per la fica ſua,</hi> which by her cunning and a falſe key (in his abſence) did open and enioy her Friend.</note> So induſtrious that ſhe is become Painter, Apothecarie, Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Barber, and what not: ſo cunning that ſhee can open the rare Venetian Locke, infect your purſe with want, and your body with the poxe: ſo chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table that (although carried in a Cart) ſhee will viſit Friends, at playes, and Bawdi-houſes: and finally, to be ſo preciſe, that ſhee that hath not cut Haire, a Fether in her Hat, a painted Face, naked Breſts, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Skirts, Piſtoles, or Poiniards, ſhall be bard her ſocietie.</p>
            <p>Secondly (to vindicate vs from the aſperſions of Noueltie) I will by your owne words, and other examples (ancient and moderne) demonſtrate the ancientie of Maſculine Women: in the ninth line of your declamation, you ſay, that ſince the dayes of <hi>Adam,</hi> Women were neuer ſo maſculine; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you couertly implie, that in the dayes of <hi>Adam, Eua,</hi> or ſome other was a Maſculine Woman; but
<pb facs="tcp:16827:5"/> admitting there was none in that age, was not <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Salomon, Samſon,</hi> enſnared with the beautie, ouercome by the multitude, and betrayed by the policie of my ſexe?<note place="margin">Mulieres ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uide<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> inep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimae, malorum vero omnium effectrices ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiſſimae, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rip. in Med.</hi>
               </note> did not <hi>Tarpeia</hi> (in later times) betray the Capitoll and her Countrey? <hi>Medea,</hi> kill her owne Children in diſpight of her Huſband? Was not <hi>Hellens</hi> lightneſſe the cauſe of the ten yeeres bloudie warre and deſtruction of Troy? did not <hi>Sylla</hi> ſteale her Fathers haire, and giue it to his Enemy? <hi>Biblis</hi> fell in loue with her owne brother; <hi>Myrrha,</hi> with her Father; <hi>Semiramis,</hi> with her ſonne. Theſe were Gallants in their time, &amp; my deare kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, by whom I hope you are ſatisfied for the ancientie of my Anceſtors: I do confeſſe at that time their number was fewer then now, yet ſufficient to pleade antiquities; but if in this age a generall mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould be taken of Women, I am ſure to draw vp in Battaile one hundreth <hi>Hos Foeminas</hi> for one <hi>Haec Foemina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in your deſcription of the Maſculine Feminine, you haue erred from the Rules of a good definition, in reducing the generall name of <hi>Haec Mulier,</hi> to thoſe you call deformed monſters, by cutting their haire, wearing French doublets, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing open breaſts and falſe bodies: but I call a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">Aequè facinori videtur obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us qui auxilium praeſtat agenti, &amp; qui perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum facinus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi iure factum collaudat, <hi>Plut. de cla. Mul.</hi>
               </note> of whatſoeuer degree, who exceedes the ends of her Creation, <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Woman was created to honour her Parents, and obey her Huſband; Fathers, to vſe their lawfull authoritie ouer their Children; Huſbands to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule &amp; command their Wiues: as he therefore is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiminate man, that transfers his birthright vpon his
<pb facs="tcp:16827:5"/> Daughter or Wife, ſo is ſhee a Maſculine Woman that bereaues Parents of authoritie,<note place="margin">A Muliere male regitur ciuitas, <hi>Ariſt. 1. Pol.</hi>
               </note> Huſbands of ſupremacie, or debords from the modeſtie required in her ſexe: ſhee then, that dare preſume to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule her Huſband (or ſometimes for his owne good beate him) although ſhee neither paint, cut her haire, or be deformed with new inuented faſhions, is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She that ſpends more vpon delicate cheere, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement of a Sweete-heart, in a moneth, then her Huſband may allow her for a yeere, is, <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She who ſitteth a goſſipping till ſhe be drunke, is,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Mulier quae vini vſum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderatè appetie vt virtutibus cunctis tanuam claudit, ita &amp; vi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ijs aperit, <hi>Max.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lingua modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum membrum, ſi refraenata non fuerit, totum corpus corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, <hi>Bern. ad Soror.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Aut appare quod es, aut eſto quod appares, <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She whoſe tongue is able to ſet the whole world on fire, or whoſe lookes, geſture, words, oathes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray her <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride, is, <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Baud that will bring you a quarte of wine in a pottle pot, an old painted Whore in ſhape of a Countrie Wench new come to Towne, is one of my kinred.</p>
            <p>The Puritan ſiſter that will crie out againſt looſe breeches, or painting, if ſhee trade with a Brother (ſo the wicked doe not ſee) is one of my Siſters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Shee that keepes a maſſe Prieſt, rather for priuate Confeſſion then publique Deuotion, is <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue now anſwered generally thoſe calumnies you doe ſuggeſt againſt me,<note place="margin">Sunt qui quod ſentiunt etiam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi oſtimum ſit, inuidiae metu non audent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, <hi>Cic. offic.</hi>
               </note> and haue ſupplyed your lame deſcription (with a full definition) of <hi>Hic Mulier.</hi> Now I will lay open your Cowardize by a ſuruey of <hi>Haec Vir,</hi> whom (not contented with
<pb facs="tcp:16827:6"/> that deſcription of the Feminine Man, lately ſet downe in a conference I had with <hi>Haec Vir</hi>) I will more fully delineate.</p>
            <p>The definition of <hi>Haec Vir</hi> (in the ſignification I now take it) ſhall not only bee extended to thoſe yong Fellowes, who deckes themſelues vp in effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate faſhions, Sweares, Swaggers, haunts Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Dicing, Carding, Tauernes, Tobacco ſhops, Ale-houſes, coſens Merchants and Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to ſupply their neuer heard of prodigalitie; but to many others of your Maſculine kind, and ſpecially to thoſe, whoſe names (according to my definition) are comprehended vnder the generaltie of <hi>Haec Vir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Paſtorum eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilare ſuper gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem propter tria neceſſaria, ad diſciplinam, ad cuſtodiam, ad preces, <hi>Bern. ſup. Cant. ſer. 42.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Imprimis,</hi> The Churchman that preferres pride, ſimony, or other worldly reſpects, before the cure of ſoules committed to his charge, is, <hi>Haec Vir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The falſe-hearted Puritan, that (vnder the vaile of deuotion) will commit all villany, take the forfeit of a poore mans bond, and dare affirme, that God ſent it him: you ſhall know him by the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing liuerie.<note place="margin">Vult hypocrita ſcire diuina elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quia, nec tamen facere, vult recte loqui, nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men viuere, <hi>Greg. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. Mor.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>They run from church to church, through all the town,</l>
               <l>They weare a thin ſmall ruffe, or bare blacke gowne.</l>
               <l>They fayne to ſpeake like Chickins when they peepe,</l>
               <l>Or leere like Cats, when they doe ſeeme to ſleepe.</l>
               <l>They make long prayers, and goggle vp their eyes,</l>
               <l>As if their zeale would teare God from the skyes.</l>
               <l>They chide at euery thing, we ſay, is good,</l>
               <l>(Excepting God) as Prince, as almes, as food:</l>
               <l>Chriſts-maſſe to name, but Chriſts-tyde, as it were</l>
               <l>Damnation, but the bare word Maſſe to heare.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16827:6"/>
               <l>They ſpeake to none that walketh in the ſtreet,</l>
               <l>Or with theſe words, God ſpeede you, any greet.</l>
               <l>Not to looke vp, but fixe on earth the eye,</l>
               <l>Apparent ſignes are of hypocriſie.</l>
               <l>God pleaſed is with playnneſſe of the hart,</l>
               <l>And not with dumbe ſhewes of the outward part.</l>
               <l>Such is their life, ſuch their Religion is,</l>
               <l>Where artes and words agree not, all's amiſſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The ſuperſticious plotting Papiſt,<note place="margin">Vindictam quam petuni Scripturae, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetia eſt non vindicta, <hi>Aug. ſup. Pſal. 66.</hi> Amor &amp; odium, &amp; proprium commodum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt ſaepe iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem non agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere veritatem, <hi>Ariſt. Rhe. 1.</hi> Maior plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lite quaeſtio eſt, <hi>Quint. Decl. 3.</hi> Paruo ab intio contentionem magnam homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus auaritia ſuppeditat; hoc vero honeſti ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines maxime cau<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant vicinis fabricare, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rip. in And.</hi>
               </note> and bloudie Ieſuite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The Iudge, who is corrupt with briberie, or ouer-ſwayed with greatneſſe, or other reſpect, then iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The Lawier, who (by too much ſtudying <hi>Ploydon</hi>) can euery day alter the Caſe, baſtardize the fundamentall Lawes by wreſted gloſſes, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming one thing this day, and another tomorrow; that hath more wit then honeſtie, and ſerues onely to emptie his Clyents Cap-caſe, and fill his owne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The Pettifogger and Atturney, who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth both wit and honeſtie, liueth altogether by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Neighbours together by the eares, are the andyrons that holds vp their Clyents, till they be burnt to aſhes, and yet are warmed themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The Vintner, that (by ſophiſticating his rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wines) makes no conſcience to hazard the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of his drunken gueſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The Taylor, that condemnes the beſt part of his Clyents garments to hell, conſumes more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in writing of a Bill, for a ſure of clothes, then might ſerue for the conueyance of one hundred pounds Land.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:7"/>
            <p>Now, if I did not pitty your cowardlineſſe, I am readie to crie out (if not ſcratch your face) for not daring challenge the baſe bloud ſucking Vſurer, neither his ſlaue the Broker.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Peior ciuis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimatur foene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator quam fur.</note>The firſt is the Caterpiller of the Common-wealth, the ouerthrow of hoſpitalitie in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, of honeſtie and trading in Cities, the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the poore, the <hi>Leuiathan</hi> that deuours thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; who (with the helpe of a Broker or Scriue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, browne bread and cheeſe) will deuoure ten, ſometimes twentie Knights eſtates.</p>
            <p>Theſe fellowes are fit fagots for hell: and if I would (as you doe) breake <hi>Priſcians</hi> head, I could call the Vſurer <hi>Hoc Vir,</hi> that is, <hi>Crudele, inſatiabile, &amp; inutile animal;</hi> fit for nothing but to be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, whereupon that ancient Roman Law, <hi>Fur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnabatur in duplum, vſurarius in quadruplum,</hi> ſhould be executed: would to God, <hi>Clinías,</hi> that the Roman Law were in England receiued, where a poore Thiefe (for ſtealing ſome goods of ſmall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue) is hanged one houre, all mercileſſe Vſurers (who neither by threatning of Gods Word, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are excluded the Kingdome of Heauen, neither by humane Lawes, wilbe reclaymed) might be hanged two houres: this cure would either end them or mend them.</p>
            <p>The Broker (skorning to bee called Vſurer) will lend none money, at ten in the hundred, vpon bond or ſecuritie, but (for ſooth) Sir if you will bring a pawne worth double the ſumme you deſire, and make a bill of Sale, you ſhall haue halfe, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the third of the value thereof: when you come
<pb facs="tcp:16827:7"/> to returne the money, and receiue your pawne, hee will either perſwade you to take ſome more money, (that it may lie till the yeere expire and it forſeit) or tell you it is in a Cheſt, where he cannot come at it, or if (perchance) you haue it, you muſt pay the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> deliuered to Miſtris Spendthrift vpon a bill of Sale, the firſt of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> 1618. for a Taffata Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticote, a Beuer Hat, Gold Band, Yellow Feather, a Fanne, a payre of Silke Stockings, Garters, and Roſes,—3<hi rend="sup">li</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> for the bill of Sale— 1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> for renewing the Bil euery three moneths 3<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> for Sir <hi>Huighes</hi> office— 1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> for nine moneths intereſt at 8<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. the moneth for the pound— 18<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Summa tot.</hi>—01<hi rend="sup">l</hi>.—03<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.—00<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</p>
            <p>This fellow is ſo cruell, that he will incroch vpon the very garments that ſhelter the poore and father leſſe. I doe know <hi>(Clinias)</hi> a poore Widdow dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by me, heere Long-lane, that hath foure young Children, who for want hath beene forced to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage (to one of thoſe Cormorants) the Couerlet of her bed, for twelue pence, and comming at night to haue it backe, ſhe could not haue it without foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene pence, and ſo in defect of two pence, ſhee and her Children were expoſed to the extremitie of cold.</p>
            <p>O adamantine hearted broker, how dareſt thou profeſſe thy ſelfe a Chriſtian, that harbors ſuch a Tigers heart? It may be thou payeſt to ſome vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered Vſurer, ten or more in the hundreth, but
<pb facs="tcp:16827:8"/> thou are not aſhamed to take from thy Chriſtian Brother aboue fiftie;<note place="margin">Turpia Incra &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lox inopes truci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, qui hoe vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſuper omnes mercantores ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictus, <hi>Chryſ. ſup. Matth.</hi>
               </note> I haue heard of a people of <hi>Scythia</hi> who are ſo addicted to couetouſneſſe, that it is lawfull for them to ſteale or purloyne from ſtrangers; but neuer did heare of any, that openly (vnpuniſhed) did prey vpon their poore neighbours to ſatiate their greedineſſe.</p>
            <p>It is not without cauſe <hi>(Clinias)</hi> that I raile thus againſt Vſurers and Brokers; for (beſides the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loſſe that redounds to the Countrey, the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall to Chriſtian profeſſion, the complaint of all good men, and the vtter ouerthrow of all charitable dealing amongſt men) I haue mine owne priuate griefes, againſt them, and am not aſhamed to tell you, that now there lyeth at a Brokers in Barbican for ſmall money, a Sattin Petticote of mine, richly layed with gold Lace, bordered with a deepe fringe of gold, a Muffe lyned with rich Furre, and a Scarfe, for all which I did pay thirtie pounds and aboue: this money was borrowed from an Vſurer vpon the bond of Maſter Woodcocke my Huſband, and goodman Gooſe our neighbour, the leaſe of our houſe pawned therewith: beſides twentie ſhillings giuen to the Scriuener to procure the money</p>
            <p>I will now leaue the Citie, and ſuruey the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Dum pacis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans agrum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueor odi ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</p>
                  <p>Vita enim ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca maximè diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncta eſt à cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditate, &amp; cum officio coniuncta <hi>Gic. pro Roſc.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> from which, thoſe of the Gentrie that ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did entertaine hoſpitalitie, their ſeruants and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers, welcomed their friends, and were helpefull to ſuch of them as ſtood in neede, are now come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cities, turned Inmates, where (with their Coach and Footemen, or (if they bee not able to keepe a Coach) their Pander, Page, vpon Whores, prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall
<pb facs="tcp:16827:8"/> cloathing, exceſſiue dyet) they ſpend all that formerly did maintaine ſo many, venting more Smoke at their noſes, then is in their Chimneyes; are altogether eſtranged both in forme, faſhion and Condition, from the rules of vertue; making often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times but a puffe of all that their fathers ſo carefully purchaſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe be of ſuch (Giant like) ſtrength,<note place="bottom">Prodigi ſunt, quo pecunias aut pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonia effude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt in eas res, quarum memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam aut bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, ant nullam ſunt relicturi omnino, <hi>Cic. 2. offie.</hi>
               </note> that by the helpe of a Merchant-Taylor, and Ieweller, will vndergoe the burthen of of a Coppie-hold vpon their ſhooeſtrings, a Freehold vpon their Garters, a Mannor vpon their ſhoulders, and a Lordſhip vpon their heads.</p>
            <p>From ſuch deuourers of eſtates, doth ariſe the improuing of lands, racking of Rents, deſtruction of ancient hoſpitalitie, and oppreſſion of poore Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Tenants. Is it not great pittie that within theſe few yeeres there be more houſholders in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land beggered (or in hazard to be) then in fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred preceading yeeres? the Gentrie hauing euer thought it their greateſt treaſure, to haue their Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Tenants able at home and abroade, in good faſhion to attend their ſeruice: but now if a Farmer, by multitude of Children, great charge, bad yeeres, death of Cattell, or other accidents (to which humane affaires are ſubiect) become poore, ſtraight comes ſome rich Graſier or remorſeleſſe V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, offers more for his Farme then it is worth; and being no ſooner offered then accepted, the poore Tenant is thruſt out of doores, and oft-times the ſmall remnant of ſtocke he hath, ſeiſed vpon for arrerages.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtitiae eſt, eſſe eius diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum tueri patrie conſuetudines, inſtituta, &amp; ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptas leges ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; ſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctatur au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem iuſtitiam &amp; ſanctitas, &amp; veritas, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, <hi>Eurip.</hi>
               </note>Looke to this, you ſenſeleſſe Land-Lords, whoſe now cauterized conſciences one day ſhall tell you, haue cruelly oppreſſed the poore, the bitter gall of whoſe teares (reſerued by the Almightie for you) without repentance and amendment, you ſhall one day drinke.</p>
            <p>Next vnto the Gentrie (the Arch-leaders of the troupes of <hi>Haec Vir</hi>) are the Iuſtices of Peace, of that ſort (I ſay, that ſort, becauſe there be others, whom for the vpright diſcharge of their places, I doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) who are either the reliques of ſome old Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer vp-ſtart Knight, or broken Barriſter, are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues fore-ſtallers of Markets, hoarders vp of corne, the ouer-ſeers of falſe meaſures, and other enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and ſometimes (without commiſeration) if it were but for their Clerks fee, will ſend a poore man to the Goale (although it ſhould vndoe him) for not putting in Suretie for his good behauiour, at the ſuite of ſome promoting Knaue, whom hee neuer offended; their chiefe ayme in keeping Seſſions and Meetings, is to find Ale-wiues, Bakers, Butchers, and ſuch others, as by priuate bribes haue not bound them to ſilence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Who did euer ſee a prouder corſe then a Knaue, riding on his Maſters horſe? <hi>Galf. chauc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hoſper non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabile genus, <hi>Eurip.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The ſawcy Conſtable, that by vertue of his Staffe will abuſe a better Subiect then himſelfe, and then charge him to the Peace in the Kings name, as if hee were authorized by his place to wrong his Betters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The cheating Inne-keeper (whereof it is likely there be ſome) who ſo racketh the Stranger or Gheſt, that before he come to the end of his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he cannot tell in which pocket his purſe is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The weather-beaten Shepheard, whoſe cunning is to make his flocke leeſe ſome of their wooll before ſhearing time,<note place="margin">Dic mihi Dame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, cuium pecus, an Moelebaei, <hi>Virg. Egl. 3.</hi>
               </note> can practize ſo with his neighbouring fellow-ſhepeard, that ſome of either flocke (by cutting off their eares or other new badge) ſhall be diſcharged their Maſters liuery, and then put the fault vpon the <hi>Foxe,</hi> Captayne <hi>Floud,</hi> or ſome vnknowne Theefe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The Miller, who thinks, the wearing of Sheeps ſattin, no pride; practiſes moſt vpon Meale, Mault, and making of Hornes.</p>
            <p>There be alſo both in Countrie and Citie, a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous broode of Feminine Maſculine, the firſt whereof is a Drunkard,<note place="margin">Ebrietas nihil aliud eſt, quam inſania volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, cor mutans, &amp; mentem alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans, <hi>Greg. ſup. 1. Reg.</hi>
               </note> hauing no more of a man but the ſhape. This fellow ſuggeſteth to himſelfe good-fellowſhip, recreation, or the bearing of much drinke; loſeth the vſe of reaſon (by which man is diſtinguiſhed from beaſt) infects his ſoule with the leproſie of ſinne, his body with diſeaſes, and his purſe with contemptible want: O, more then beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vice to reigne amongſt Chriſtians, which was not knowne to the Ethnickes, as appeareth by one, thus complayning:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hos homines non putaſſent Ethnici, ſed pertentoſa hominum monſtra &amp; porcos, ſe vino obruentes at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurgiantes, vltra corporis menſuram, &amp; ventris ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitatem, ad perdenda vina orti; verùm quod Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis turpiſsimum, multis noſtrae aetatis videtar valde glorioſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond (an inſeparable fellow to Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe)
<pb facs="tcp:16827:10"/> is blaſphemie,<note place="margin">Dico v<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>bis ne iurate omnino, ne iurando ad facilitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di veniatur, de facilitate ad conſuetudinem, de conſuetudine in periurium, de periurio in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernum decida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Aug. contr. Mend.</hi>
               </note> ſimpathizing rather with the nature of Deuils then of men, or beaſts, vſing the tongue that ought to bee the Herald of God his glorie, to be the proclaimer of moſt horrible blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt him, tearing his body, heart, and ſoule in peeces; this is the moſt accurſed ſlaue that liueth, who without any colour (as all other ſinnes haue) takes armes againſt Gods owne perſon; hee is accounted in this age (amongſt Feminine men) the braueſt Gallant, that can ſweare the moſt rare and new inuented oath extempore: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon oathes (that formerly were not heard, or ſo religiouſly looked vnto, that a knowne ſwearer was barred all honeſt ſocietie) are now transferred vpon Clownes, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termen, Carre<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men, and others of the meaneſt ſort; who together with their Leaders (without earneſt repentance) ſhall one day pay deere for ſuch vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Ware as they haue taken at ſo ſo deere a rate: againſt whom the Satyriſt thus ſpeaketh,
<q>
                  <l>Per Solis radios, Tarpeia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fulmina iurant,</l>
                  <l>Et Martis frameam &amp; Cyrrhaei ſpicula vatis,</l>
                  <l>Per calamos venatricis, pharetram<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> puellae,</l>
                  <l>Quicquid habent telorum armamentaria Coeli.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Animal inter omnia noxium eſt, inter mitia adulator, <hi>Bias apud Plut.</hi>
               </note>In the next place commeth the flatterer, rightly called the moſt cruell of tame beaſts, hee is no leſſe hatefull to the Wiſe, then beloued of Fooles: hee is the deuourer of all ſuch as truſt him, the poyſon of truth, the impudent maintayner of falſe colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red lyes, the enemie to vpright dealing and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. Hee names lecherie, true loue; drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:16827:10"/> good fellowſhip; deceit, policie; crueltie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>buſu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> luge<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> quo vitae reputantu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, <hi>apud Stob.</hi>
               </note> manhood; niggardly auarice, good huſbandry. If his Patron bee angrie, hee is mad, if merrie, hee laughes; if ſad, (with the Crocodile) hee weepes; if offended with his Friend, he perſwades him neuer to be reconciled; if his maſter bee a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, his flatterer loues muſicke out of meaſure; if he be a Faulconer, he loues hawking, although hee cannot diſcerne a Falcon from a Kite, neither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from a Woodcocke.</p>
            <p>This Camelion can turne himſelfe into all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loures, following mens fortunes, not themſelues, and is a diſh fitter for the Diuel, then for a wiſe, noble, or generous mind. That you may know him by his habit, reade the worthy ſaying of <hi>Aagapetus</hi> to <hi>Iuſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pellaces adulatorum ſermones auerfare, vt coruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum rapaces mores: Illi nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Corporis effodiunt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos, iſti autem animi hebetant cogitatus, cum non permittant perſpicere rerum veritatem: vel enim commendant, nonnunquam quae reprehenſione digna ſunt, vel reprehendunt plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quae omni laude ſunt maiora, vt de duobus alterum ab ipſis committatur, vel prauorum laus, vel bonorum criminatio: ſub a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leatore paſsim luditur alea, ſub bellaci bellaturiunt, ſub commeſſatore luxu defluunt, ſub ebrio ebrij ſunt, ſub libidinoſo lenocinantur, ſub crudeli deferunt ac calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place ſucceedeth the moſt cruell of wilde Beaſts (too frequent in Countrie and Citie)
<pb facs="tcp:16827:11"/> called a Detracter.<note place="margin">Detraectio amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia venenum, patientiam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram lingua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perea probans: bonum quod eſt, abſcondit, &amp; malum quod non eſt mentitur, <hi>Greg. ſerm. 65.</hi>
               </note> This Eſopicall Foxe buildeth his chiefe reputation vpon the infamie of others; whom hee may vndermine or ſlander is his morning and euening meditation: hee is as very a coward as you <hi>Clinias;</hi> his hotteſt purſuite is euer behind backe, and his moſt deadly blowes are with proteſtation of meaning no harme, or with a diſſimulate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue pittie of the partie: Hee is moſt ſlauiſhly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, and knoweth the art of words ſo well, that he can ſhrowd diſhoneſtie vnder a faire pretext, and is like to him that preſerues poiſon in a golden Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell Finally, he is the moſt baſe amongſt men, and to be excluded honeſt ſocietie, according to that of the Philoſopher:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vir bonus &amp; circumſpectus aures Suſurronibus &amp; calumniat oribus praebere non debet, qui perſaepe aures noſtras ita praeoccupant innocentes criminando, vt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficillimum ſit id ex praecordijs euellere, quod falſus criminator infixit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could now ioyne iſſue with you, that I haue rightly named you <hi>Clinias;</hi> that I haue prooued thoſe imputations you lay againſt vs Maſculine Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, are the moſt honorable ends we ayme at, and that the deſcription of <hi>Hic Mulier</hi> and <hi>Haec Vir</hi> is further extended then to the weakeſt of Women and moſt fooliſh of men: I am ſure (although the Iurie were ſo couetous that ten Groates would moue more then a iuſt cauſe) if you keepe your purſe cloſe, the Verdict will goe on my ſide: but I am deſirous to come to a more friendly end with
<pb facs="tcp:16827:11"/> you, by offering a reformation of thoſe things you lay againſt me, and my kindred, prouided that <hi>Haec Vir</hi> and his Friends ſhall performe the articles fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimis,</hi> That ſuch Church men, who <hi>(vt haec Vir)</hi> haue gone out of the way, (laying aſide Pride, Vaine-glorie, Couetouſneſſe, and all other worldly reſpects) remember that they muſt anſwer for their charge, and hereafter feede their Flocks,<note place="margin">In iudicio Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores cum ſuis gregibus appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, <hi>Gregor. Mor. 33.</hi>
               </note> and aboue all goe before them in a good and vnreproueable life, becauſe good Examples edifie more then Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as it is well ſaid to this purpoſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non eſt alia breuior aut efficacior ad corrigendos populi mores via, quàm regentis ipſius incorrupta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta; quae ſi turpibus contaminata flagitijs, etſi caput ipſum peſtilens fuerit, latiùs tamen virus ſerpit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all Iudges (if any ſuch be) who haue beene corrupted with bribes, tranſported with reuenge,<note place="margin">Pluit vitium, vbi pluit aurum <hi>Greg. in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt.</hi>
               </note> fauour, or feare, haue notice that hee ought to face a man of courage, vpright, and fearing God; that he is lyable to puniſhment from God in the heauens,<note place="margin">Peſſimè iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur falsò iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantes, <hi>Aug. ſup. Pſal. 25.</hi>
               </note> and his Prince vpon earth. Let his chiefe meditation be vpon the great charge of Vicegerency, committed to him from both; remembring what danger hee is in here and hereafter, if his obiect be not iuſtice, if hee defend not the Poore, Widow, and Fatherleſſe, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Mightie:<note place="margin">Iudicantes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mente prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos eſſe opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, qua legis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores Liſias, <hi>apud Stob.</hi>
               </note> if he ſquare not his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſometimes rather by Conſcience then Caſes; if he preferre not the publique good before his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate gayne, miniſter not by his life the due executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:16827:12"/> of Lawes, and euer lay before him theſe foure following grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Iudicium rectum verum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non cernit Iudex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, odio vel pecania corruptus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Iudex ſententiam haud proferre debet, niſi vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> parte diligenter audita; quod niſi fecerit, licèt aequum ſtatuerit, haud tamen iuſtus erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Iudicis officium est non tantùm res, ſed &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora perſcrutari, quo peracto tutus erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Heroes iustitiae miniſtri primùm ipſi ſint iuſti oportet, &amp; immaculata prius omnis honeſtatis exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaria, quàm importuni vitiorum correctores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lis de rebus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile corruptibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus celeriter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminari debet, vel res vende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud iuriſconſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, <hi>Plut. de Pol.</hi>
               </note>That ſuch Lawyers who formerly haue ſtudied to continue ſuites, or haue ſhared (by indirect meanes) in priuate benefit both from plaintife and defendant, ſhall forth with recall themſelues; leſt I giue this cenſure againſt them:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In nullos ſeueriùs animaduer tendum quàm in Iuris conſultos ac officiarios, quorum prauitas, aut auaritia, rectè institutas leges ad peſsimos vſus detorquet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Publicae cont a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictiones &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſia ſi offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciariorum offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones ſubducas leuiores effici ſolent, <hi>Plut. de Pol.</hi>
               </note>That all Attorneyes and Pettifoggers (whereof there is greater ſtore in euery Market towne, and in ſome Villages, then formerly hath beene in a whole Countrey) who now ſtriues (by ſetting neighbors at ſtrife) for multitude of Clyents, may either become peace makers, or diſcharge the truſt repoſed in them, or then acknowledge that they maintaine this <hi>Maximum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucrum, pudori praeſtat, &amp; lucri bonus odor è re qualibet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all Puritans (who thinke euery idle ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion conſonant to their burning braynes lawfull,<note place="margin">Nouitas contra Eccleſiae ritum non placet, eſt enim mater te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritaris, ſoror ſuperſtitionis, &amp; filiae leuitatis, <hi>Bern. in Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> can ſee nothing in others but (through the glaſſe of preiudicate opinions, deformities and abuſes) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them ſelues to the vniformitie of ſpirituall and ciuill gouernement, leſt this ſaying of <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> be iuſtly applyed to them:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tanquam de Deo ac re omnium maxima ſalute<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ipſa primaria<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſpe certamen habentes, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> obſequium non pietatem ſed veritatis proditionem interpretan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, omnia antè proiecerint, quàm opiniones quas dome ſecum afferunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all plotting Papiſts, ſeminarie Prieſts,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Omne fidoi dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſacris ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruens ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſum eſt,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſ. Hom. 1.</hi> Omnibus eſt odio erudilitas &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mori pictas, <hi>Gic.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Ieſuites, hoorded in Countrey and City, take their oath of allegiance, imbrace the truth, become good Subiects, by forſaking deuilliſh imaginations, ſuperſtitious and humane traditions, or then retire themſelues to Rome, keeping this Warrant:
<q>
                  <l>Roma quid inſanis? quid in impietate triumphas?</l>
                  <l>Quid nectis fraudes? ſtupráue faeda colis?</l>
                  <l>Concubitus vetitus cordi eſt, puerilis amor<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</l>
                  <l>Impurus cultus, vana ſuperſtitio?</l>
                  <l>Dicitur illa quidem meretrix &amp; adultera turpis,</l>
                  <l>Agnoſcit plures quae vitiata viros.</l>
                  <l>Illa vrbs non aliter, coluit quae numina plura,</l>
                  <l>Scortum eſt: hoc Babilon, impia Roma facit.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16827:13"/>
                  <l>Vrbs Romana potest meretrix Babilonia dici,</l>
                  <l>Quae coluit ſpreto numina plura Deo.</l>
                  <l>Illa deos coluit plures, ſimulacra lareſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</l>
                  <l>Quaeſtum, diuitias, gaudia falſa, dapes;</l>
                  <l>Pompas, luxuriam, ventrem, pueroſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> doloſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> malos genios, ſtupra, venena, lupas.</l>
                  <l>Papae fuit quondam meretrix, peperit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> platea,</l>
                  <l>Cuius Imago tibi Romae ſtat conſpicienda.</l>
                  <l>Roma diu titubans, longis erroribus aucta,</l>
                  <l>Corruet, &amp; mundi deſinet eſſe caput.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That all Citizens, Merchants, and Tradeſmen, from the higheſt to the loweſt (that fight vnder the colours of <hi>Haec Vir</hi>) neither ſophiſticate their wares, neither ſell them at higher rates,<note place="margin">Nemo habet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtum lucrum fine iuſto damno, <hi>Aug ſerra. 48.</hi>
               </note> then (with reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gaine) they may maintaine their charge; but more ſpecially that they ſell no rotten Pepper, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Clones, and other Indian traſh, at double rate, to yong heires vpon ſtatutes; leſt by a former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyance they loſe both principall and intereſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<q>
                  <l>Iudice me fraus est, conceſſa, repellere fraudem,</l>
                  <l>Arma<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in armatos ſumere iura ſinunt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In hac artium ſola euenit vt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> medicum profeſſo, ſtatim credatur, cum ſit periculum in nullo mendacio maius, <hi>Plin. ſent. 29.</hi>
               </note>That good examination and triall preceede the admiſſion of Doctors of Phiſicke, Apothecaries, Chirurgeons, and Empiricks that are of this order; leſt they kill more in a yeere then they cure in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and giue their Patients iuſt cauſe to pray:
<q>Amedico indocto libera me Domine.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:13"/>
            <p>That all Vſurers and Brokers,<note place="margin">Habes, ne foene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reris quia non indiges: non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, ne foenereris quia ſatisfacere non potes, <hi>Plut. de Vſur.</hi>
               </note> leaue their biting bargaines, and either conuert their moneyes to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt purchaſe, husbandry in the Countrey, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture it vpon more lawfull trade in the Citie; by vertue of the following reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tollendus penitus Faenerator, ne (ſub quouis praetex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu populi detrimento) foediſsimum illud vitae genus exerceatur: quiſquis enim pecuniae ſtudium tollet, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum neruos reſecabit: vbi enim pecuniae amor, ibi fides, probitas, pudor, amicitia, &amp; omnia bona vilia ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſuch of the Gentrie as are vniuſtly diſpoſſeſt of their countrey habitations (by Iacke-dawes,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Infeſtiſsima ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus poſſeſſio eſt ager, <hi>apud Stob.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Primum luxuria ciuitates ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, deinde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitas, poſtea contumelia, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtea exilium, <hi>Thucid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quicquid pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peri dederis, tu habebis: quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid non dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, alter habebit, <hi>Pet. Rau.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Owles, and night-Crowes) ſhall preſently repoſſeſſe themſelues and keepe reſidence till their Princes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or ſome other vrgent neceſſitie withdraw them; baniſh all prodigall charges, (to which Cities are moſt ſubiect) and in liew thereof maintaine frugall hoſpitality, educate their Children religiouſly, be a comfort to their friends, repayre the now decayed eſtate of poore Farmers and Tenants, and inueſt themſelues in the true nobilitate vertues of their anceſtors; for nobilitie without vertue, is a ſhadow without ſubſtance, according to the Stagiricke ſaying:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nobilitas est quaedam maiorum claritas &amp; laus veniens de meritis parentum; ſed ea natiuum decus ſuum in filijs amittit, ſi parentum virtutibus non reſponderint; nam nobilitas cognatorum nobis non
<pb facs="tcp:16827:14"/> prodeſt, niſi fuerimus nos ipſi boni; quanto enim vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, maiorum praeclarior, tanto posteriorum ſocordia flagitioſior eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe aboue named are the chiefe perſons whoſe reformation ſhall binde vs Maſculine Women to the good behauiour: others there bee whom I will not grace, by couenanting with them, becauſe they are almoſt (if not altogether) paſt hope of recouerie, and threfore I exclude them from any benefit of this agreement.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Informer and promoting Knaue (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a thouſand of whom one honeſt man is hardly found) whoſe firſt inſtitution was to enforme the Kings Courts of abuſes prohibited by Law; for which ſeruice the halfe of ſuch fines as by the Law (by their information) was recouerable, was allowed to them; but this commendable beginning is ſo depraued and inuerted by the multitude of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding Vagabonds (proiecting nothing but their owne benefit) that the innocent are rather troubled then the guiltie puniſhed,<note place="margin">Iniquum eſt vt nocens poenam euadat, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt innocens plecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Quintil.</hi>
               </note> compoſitions drawne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore triall, the King defrauded, and his Courts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> all hard harted Iaylors who (like the Cat) playes with his trembling priſoner,<note place="margin">Maxima pars hominum qui carceribus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feruntur, ſitut illu ſubiecti, praedae ſunt, ita illi (fine reſipiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia) ſaepe diabolo, <hi>apud Stob.</hi>
               </note> ſo long as his purſe is able to defray their exorbitant exactions, &amp; then preyes ſo vpon his decaying body, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhort time his obſtinate Creditor may make Dice of his bones</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> All bankrupt Serieants and Baylifes, the Iaylors bloud-hounds, that (at Chancery Lane end,
<pb facs="tcp:16827:14"/> the Exchange, Fleet-ſtreet, Strond, Kings-ſtreet,<note place="margin">Licet eni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſit, tamen qui contra pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem tale offi i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um exercent pro nebulonibus ſunt habendi, <hi>Reinb. Lor.</hi> Homines non facile decipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, niſi in eo quod neſciunt, aut in eo, cuius cognitio non eſt valde manifeſta. <hi>Ariſt. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph. 4.</hi>
               </note> and elſewhere thorowout England) hunts more greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after a decayed Debtor, then the Lyon or Wolfe after a ſlow Aſſe, or innocent Lambe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> All cheating Horſe-courſers, who (by tricks and oathes) ſell lame jades, fatted by grames or other traſh, to ignorant ſtrangers, or purſe-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten trauellers, at greater price then the skin and ſhooes are worth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The ingrain'd Oſtler, who ſells his Hay by the bottle (or rather bootfull) can furniſh ſix pecks out of a buſhell of Market meaſure at double rate, and (if hee hath not anointed the Trauellers Horſe teeth) will draw the beſt part of his allowance backe to the Oſterie; and if this ſerue not, will picke a ſhooe from your Horſe, breake your Bridle, ſteale your Girth, or giue notice of the weight of your Cloke-bagge, leſt hee fayle in correſpondence with his ancient confederates, the Smith, Sadler, and high way Robber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> All high-way Rogues, that ſells Callico for Cambricke, watered white yron hilts for hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſiluer, Dutch ſixe-penny blades for vpright To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledoes, deceiues young Nouices and old Gulls with traſh, impoſture, and deceitfull ware.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> All counterfait ſtrong Beggers,<note place="margin">Elcemoſyna ad neceſſitatem non ad pigritiam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip end 1, <hi>Aug: de oper. Mon.</hi>
               </note> who (by high-wayes and other places) goe lame all day, and whole at night.</p>
            <p>Now, to vntie all that I haue knit vp in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, I doe aduiſe all ſuch that may come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Haec Vir,</hi> or (who miſgouernes themſelues, and are the ſtumbling blocks whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:16827:15"/> others fall,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Durum eſt, vt qui neſcit tenere moderamina vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſuae, iudex fiat vita aliena, <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Parere filios ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatis opus, rectè autem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducare pij amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, <hi>Eurip. apud. Stob.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>) firſt remoue thoſe miſty clouds of darkeneſſe, that now ouer-ſhadowes their owne ſight, and then boldly preſume to cleare the eyes of others; that they goe before vs in imbracing of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſhunning of vice, and by good education enter vs in the pathes of modeſtie, from which now we are eſtranged: and then (without doubt) we that are the weaker Veſſels (now onely miſſe-led by the ouer-ſight of careleſſe Parents, or indulgence of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate husbands, are let looſe to all licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) ſhall in ſhort time caſt off all ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities, wherewith you now taxe vs. And ſo (becauſe I muſt make mee vnready and goe to a maske) I bid you good night.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16827:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
